Guide to the Albert Cornell, M.D. Collection of Medical Ephemera, 1910-2004 RL.00259
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Albert Cornell, M.D. collection of medical ephemera
1910-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cornell, Albert
RL.00259
4 Linear Feet 1500 items
Retired Chief of the Gastrointestinal Clinic at Mount Sinai Hospital.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Albert Cornell, M.D. Collection of Medical Ephemera was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006.
Biographical Note
Dr. Cornell was a consultant in gastroenterology at the Mount Sinai Medical Center and the retired Chief of the Gastrointestinal Clinic at Mount Sinai Hospital.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of medical and pharmaceutical advertisements and promotional materials. Included are posters, booklets, diet guides, recipe books, artifacts (coffee mugs, paperweights, etc.) and other promotional ephemera. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Advertising, Sales & Marketing History.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Advertising Ephemera Collection
Roy Lightner Collection of Antique Advertisements
Calendars; Posters; Advertising -- Health products; Advertising -- Pharmaceutical industry; Advertising -- Medicine; Cornell, Albert; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- Printed Materials, 1910-2004 and undated; 1; 4 boxes
  - Abbott Laboratories
    - Butyn Sulfate advertisement, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Pentothal Sodium postcard, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Pollen products, undated (Box 1)
    - The Treatment of Syphilis, 1938 (Box 1)
  - A.H. Robins--Dimetapp note pad, 1975 (Box 1)
  - A.H. Robins--Donnatal, 1969-1985 (Box 1)
  - American Dental Association
    - Good Teeth for Young America, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Healthy Teeth, undated (Box 1)
    - Little Red Sky, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Your Teeth and Their Care, 1944 (Box 1)
  - American Dietaids--Souplets, Joyana, Brevy letter to physicians, undated (Box 1)
  - American Ferment--Al-Caroid (antacid) card, undated (Box 1)
  - American Medical Association
    - Annual meeting brochure, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - Daily Bulletin, 1947 June 12 (Box 1)
    - List of exhibitors, Technical Exposition, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Today's Health, 1957 June (Box 1)
  - Anedemin Chemical--Anedemin tablets advertisement, undated (Box 1)
  - Arch Laboratories--Peptic Ulcer Guide, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Arlington Chemical--Acute Lymphatic Leukemia, undated (Box 1)
  - Arlington Chemical--Differential Leucocyte Count of Blood, 1930 (Box 1)
  - BectonDickinson & Co.--Ace bandage and hosiery calendar booklet, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Borcherdt--Note pad, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Bristol Laboratories
    - Bristol Digest, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - Penicillin, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Polycycline advertisement, undated (Box 1)
  - Broadway Medical Registry for Nurses--Key Guide to the Streets and Avenues of New York City, undated (Box 1)
  - Burroughs Wellcome
    - Dexin High Dextrin Carbohydrate for Infant and Adult Feeding, undated (Box 1)
    - Empirin note pad, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Kepler, Tabloid, Emocin, Dexin brochures, circa 1940s (Box 1)
    - Ryzamin-B Rice Polishings Concentrate brochure, undated (Box 1)
  - Burrows--Burrows Book of Appointments, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Campbell Products--Regime for the Use of Mercurin Suppositories, undated (Box 1)
  - Canadian Medical Association Journal--Further History of the Care and Feeding of the Dionne Quintuplets, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Ciba Pharmaceuticals--Innervation of the Biliary System, undated (Box 1)
  - Ciba Pharmaceuticals--Major Pathology of Heart and Aorta, 1940 (Box 1)
  - City of New York, Department of Health--Quarterly Bulletin, 1910, 1942, 1951 (Box 1)
  - City of New York, Department of Hospitals--Envelope, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous charts, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous recipes and instruction sheets, undated (Box 1)
  - Dannon/Beatrice Foods--The Psychology of Dieting, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Dannon Milk Company--Dieting to Reduce, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Davol Rubber--R.W. Sengstaken Nasogastric Tube advertisement, undated (Box 2)
  - Dietene Company--Dietine/Meritene diet guides, undated (Box 2)
  - East Harlem Health Center--Social Hygiene bulletin, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Edwards--Orthopedic shoes for children brochure, undated (Box 2)
  - Eli Lilly
    - Ampoules Thevetin brochure, undated (Box 2)
    - Darvocet calendar pad, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Darvocet-N 100/Darvon note pad, undated (Box 2)
    - Entoral brochure, circa 1940s (Box 2)
    - Lilly Diet Chart, undated (Box 2)
    - Physician's Bulletin, 1948 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Pulvules Lextron (liver concentrate), undated (Box 2)
  - E.R. Squibb
    - Handbook for Diabetics, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Insulin and Non-Diabetic Malnutrition, circa 1930s (Box 2)
    - Syrup Senodin brochure, undated (Box 2)
  - Fujisawa--Her Heart calendar, 2004 (Box 2)
  - G.D. Searle
    - Colonic Stasis, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Lomotil/Metamucil/Pro-Banthine--Gastrointestinal Anatomy tear-off pad, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Research in the Service of Medicine v.14: Roentgen Studies of Spastic Phenomena of the Gastrointestinal Tract, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Research in the Service of Medicine v.27: Recent Advances in Therapy of Peptic Ulcer, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Searle Library of Medical Plates: Colitis; Intestinal Innervation, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Geigy--My Doctor--A Child's Eye View, 1965 (Box 2)
  - General Baking Company--Food for Sound Teeth, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Hoechst Pharmaceuticals --Lasix Furosemide note pad, undated (Box 2)
  - Keefe & Keefe--Friendly Chat, 1955 Apr. (Box 2)
  - Kellogg Company--Diet Series pamphlets, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Knox Gelatine
    - Bland Diets for Gastritis and Peptic Ulcer, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Do You Really Want to Lose Weight?, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Feeding Diabetic Patients Young and Old, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Feel Fit As a Fiddle After 40, by Don Herold, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Meal Planning for the Sick and Convalescent, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Peptic Ulcer Dietary, circa 1940s (Box 2)
    - Reducing Diets and Recipes, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Lakeside Pharmaceuticals--Bentyl--Irritable Bowel Syndrome, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Lederle Laboratories
    - An Advance in Parenteral Liver Therapy--Intramuscular Injection, circa 1930s (Box 2)
    - Bellabulgara (belladonna root extract), 1940 (Box 2)
    - Bulletin, 1939 Feb. (Box 2)
    - Liver Extract in the Treatment of Pernicious Anemia, circa 1930s (Box 2)
    - Minocin note pad, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Perihemin postcard, undated (Box 2)
    - Playbill silver anniversary edition reprint (Pathibamate), 1982 (Box 2)
    - Prevention of Communicable Diseases in Childhood, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Therapeutic Application of Digitalis, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Treatment of Pernicious Anemia with Solution Liver Extract, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Vi-Magna vitamins--Sympathetic Nervous System plate, undated (Box 2)
  - Life Extension Institute --Health survey, 1923 (Box 3)
  - Lydia O'Leary--Covermark--How to Use It, undated (Box 3)
  - Lydia O'Leary--Covermark, the Modern Miracle, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Machlett Laboratories--Dynamax x-ray tube brochure, undated (Box 3)
  - Maltine--Proloid thyroid medication card, undated (Box 3)
  - McKesson & Robbins--First Aid in Emergencies, undated (Box 3)
  - Mead Johnson
    - Brochure to physicians, circa 1930s (Box 3)
    - Dextri-Maltose advertisement, undated (Box 3)
    - Klotrix note pad, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Preparing the Infant's Food, with Cod Liver Oil Psychology, undated (Box 3)
  - Merck Sharp & Dohme
    - Genitourinary plate, undated (Box 3)
    - Low-Residue Diet, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Rheumatoid Arthritis/Gout booklet (Indolin), 1967 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Arlington Chemical/Aminoids; Sanka coffee; Katherine Storm supports; Nabisco Shredded Wheat; Glyco-Thymoline; Eskay's Pentaplex; Bircher ultraviolet lamp; Saraka laxative; Nason's Supertah; Johnson mustard plaster; Cooper creme contraceptive; undated. (Box 3)
    - Articles on pneumonia, 1929-1933 (Box 3)
    - Baumanometer blood pressure gauge; Ralston cereals; Hamilton examination furniture; Tarbonis cream; Kondremul laxative; Anusol suppositories; Santa's health inspection; Musterole; Trimble nursery furniture; Par-Pen (Paredrine+Penicillin); Dr. Scholl's arch supports; Bisodol mints; Shampaine medical cabinets, circa 1940s (Box 3)
    - Diet forms, undated (Box 3)
    - Office pads, undated (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Vitamins and dieting, circa 1930s (Box 3)
    - Wm. S. Merrell Nitranitol; Eskay's Theranates; Schieffelin Benzestrol estrogen therapy; More Doctors Smoke Camels advertisement, circa 1940s (Box 3)
  - Montefiore Home--Examination (autopsy?) forms, undated (Box 3)
  - Montefiore Hospital--Eye examination charts, undated (Box 3)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital--Diet forms, undated (Box 3)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital--Fractional Gastric Analysis/Stomach Contents charts, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital--The New Gewalter, 1952 Apr. 19 (Box 3)
  - National Drug Company--Aminovite Recipes, undated (Box 3)
  - National Life Insurance Company--Quotes & Notes--What About Your Retirement?, 1952 (Box 3)
  - National Foundation for Infant Paralysis--Information for Physicians on the Salk Poliomyelitis Vaccine, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Nestle--Lactogen Obstetric Table, undated (Box 3)
  - New York Academy of Medicine--Preventive Medicine, 1938 July (Box 3)
  - New York Physician--New York Physician and American Medicine, 1951 Dec. (Box 3)
  - New York Tuberculosis and Health Association--Christmas stamps, 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Norgine Laboratories--Enzypan postcard, circa 1950s (Box 3)
  - Organon--Trevidol--You'd Roar Too (verse by Richard Armour, illustrations by Leo Hershfield). Undated (Box 4)
  - Parke Davis/Bay Company--Chromographs of Surgical Pathology, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Pfizer--Renese brochure with art prints from Utrillo and Degas, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Pfizer--Terramycin booklet, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Ralston Purina--Low Calorie Diet, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Rowell/Monarch/Salix--Cortenema/Proctocort/Hydrocil--Anatomical drawings of gastrointestinal tract, tear-off pad, undated (Box 4)
  - Sandoz Pharmaceuticals
    - Cafergot/Fiorinal mailer, circa 1953 (Box 4)
    - Medical Horizons, vol. 3 no. 1-3, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
    - Sandoz Pharmacology and Therapy: No. 1--Migraine, circa 1940s (Box 4)
  - Schenley Laboratories--Penicillin in Emphema, circa 1947 (Box 4)
  - Schering
    - A Rational Approach to the Treatment of the Post-Climacteric (Menopause), 1946 (Box 4)
    - Genitourinary Tract Anatomy for the Patient, 1947 (Box 4)
    - Pelvic Anatomy for the Patient--Normal and Abnormal Conditions, 1941 (Box 4)
    - Pelvic Anatomy for the Patient, 1947 (Box 4)
    - Schering Introduces You to Origami, undated (Box 4)
    - Shock: Its Prevention with Cortate Routine, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Searle/Blue Cross Association--Lomotil--A Foreign Language Guide to Health Care, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Smith Kline & French
    - Envelope, undated (Box 4)
    - Eskacillin (liquid penicillin) brochure, undated (Box 4)
    - Feosol Hemoglobin Scale, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Medical Color Television Program, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Your Tensions and How to Live with Them, undated (Box 4)
  - Sonotone (hearing aids)--Tradition of Service (collection of advertisements), 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Sterling Drug--Talwin telephone pad, undated (Box 4)
  - Tampax--Standing Female Pelvic Organs/Female Reproductive Organs, anatomical plates, undated (Box 4)
  - The Bloodless Phlebotomist--Some Points in the Treatment of Pneumonia, undated (Box 4)
  - Unidentified
    - Diets for Expectant and Nursing Mothers, 1933 (Box 4)
    - Early Signs of a Heart Attack, undated (Box 4)
    - Instructions for Expectant Mothers, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Upjohn--Ulcerative Colitis, 1960 (Box 4)
  - White Laboratories--A Vitamin Alphabet, 1940 (Box 4)
  - William H. Rorer--Maalox--Fritatta recipe card, 1983 (Box 4)
  - William R. Warner--Peptic Ulcer: A Disease of Civilization, undated (Box 4)
  - Williams & Wilkins--Current Medical Digest, 1938 Nov. (Box 4)
  - Winthrop Chemical--Physician's Handbook, undated (Box 4)
  - Wyeth Laboratories
    - Bicillin advertisement, undated (Box 4)
    - Intragastric Drip Therapy for Peptic Ulcer, undated (Box 4)
    - Medical Men of the Day, caricatured by Ape and Spy, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Petrolagar--Bowel plates/advertisement, undated (Box 4)
    - Your Ulcer--And How It Grows; patient instruction aid, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Parke, Davis--A History of Medicine in Pictures, vol. 2, illustrated by Robert A. Thom, 1958 (Box 5)
- Artifacts, 1935-1986 and undated; 2; 3 boxes
  - A.H. Robins--Robitussin--Rain bonnet, undated (Box 5)
  - Abbott Laboratories--Enduron/Enduronyl/Eutron--Theraputic Building Blocks trowel, undated (Box 5)
  - Abbott Laboratories--Fero-Grad 500/Fero-Folic 500/Iberet 500--Golf balls, undated (Box 5)
  - American Cyanamide--Pathibamate--All-purpose tool in case, undated (Box 5)
  - Conference pin, Atlantic City, 1942 (Box 5)
  - Conference pin, Atlantic City, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Convention guest pin, undated (Box 5)
  - Meeting guest pin, undated (Box 5)
  - Bay Ridge Savings Bank--Chest X-Ray reminder--Needle threader, undated (Box 5)
  - Chemical Specialties--Norinyl--Magnets, undated (Box 5)
  - Ciba Pharmaceuticals--Letter opener/magnifying glass, undated (Box 5)
  - Eli Lilly--Medical history card holder, undated (Box 5)
  - Eli Lilly--Nail file and holder, undated (Box 5)
  - Fancy Free Maternity Shop--Nail emery board, undated (Box 5)
  - G.D. Searle--Diuol--Ball point pen, undated (Box 5)
  - Glenn's--Glenn's Thermometer Sterilizer, undated (Box 5)
  - Hoechst Pharmaceuticals --Topicort--Coaster, undated (Box 5)
  - Hoffman-La Roche--Berocca Plus--Paperweight, undated (Box 5)
  - Johnson & Johnson--Imodium--Sunglasses with case, undated (Box 5)
  - Lederle Laboratories
    - Asendin--Keychain medallion, undated (Box 5)
    - Ferro-Sequels--6" ruler, undated (Box 5)
    - Pathibamate--Paperweight, undated (Box 5)
  - Marion Laboratories--Nico-400--Paperclip, undated (Box 5)
  - McNeil --Butisol--6"/150mm ruler, undated (Box 5)
  - McNeil --Tylenol--4"/100mm ruler and paperclip, undated (Box 5)
  - Mead Johnson--Dextri-Maltose--Physician's Handy Formulae Feeding Calculator, 1935 (Box 5)
  - Mead Johnson/Bristol Myers--Sewing kit, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Merck & Co.
    - Aldoril--Ruler/magnifying glass, undated (Box 5)
    - Mefoxin--Nail clipper, undated (Box 5)
    - Moduretic--Safety light, undated (Box 5)
    - Pepsid--Rainbow-colored ball point pen, undated (Box 5)
  - Merrill Dow--Bentyl--Paper clip with colon, undated (Box 5)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital--Silverware (Knife, fork, spoons), undated (Box 5)
  - Mount Sinai School of Medicine--Pillbox, Celebration of the First Commencement, 1970 May 27 (Box 5)
  - Northeast Electronics (Nuclear medicine)--Plastic paper clip, undated (Box 5)
  - Nycomed Gmbh--Riopan--Watch Your Salt! magnet, undated (Box 5)
  - Parke Davis --Chloromycetin--6"/150mm ruler, undated (Box 5)
  - Parke Davis --Tabron--Fetus paperweight, undated (Box 5)
  - Pfizer--Atarax--Grooming knife, undated (Box 5)
  - Plough--St. Joseph's Aspirin for Children--Physician's sample packets, undated (Box 5)
  - Rexall Drug Stores--AMA MD New York City keychain medallion, undated (Box 5)
  - Ross Laboratories--Phone message holder, undated (Box 5)
  - Schering--Trilafon--Plastic object, undated (Box 5)
  - Scully-Walton (Ambulance and therapy service)--Sewing kit, undated (Box 5)
  - Smith Kline & French--Eska-Deck playing cards (feature images of foods with calorie information), 1969 (Box 5)
  - Stuart Pharmaceuticals--Mylanta/Mylicon/Dialose-Plus/Kinesed--Petite nail kit, undated (Box 5)
  - Unidentified
    - Ex Libris label showing Sites of Intellectual Processes (c. 1500), undated (Box 5)
    - Plastic object with anatomical drawing, undated (Box 5)
    - Post-It note pad in the form of a match book: Smoking Has Increased His Coronary Risk/Have You Asked Him About Erectile Dysfunction (E.D.)?, undated (Box 5)
    - The Heart in Essential Hypertension (plastic plate, apparently one of a series), undated (Box 5)
    - Tie clasp featuring image of gastrointestinal tract, undated (Box 5)
  - Upjohn--Cortef--protractor, undated (Box 5)
  - USV Pharmaceuticals--Doxy-II--Thermometer card, Let's Help Each Other During the Energy Crisis, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Wyeth Laboratories--Pen-Vee oral penicillin, feather pen, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Dr. Barnett L. Becker, Optometrist--12" ruler, undated (Box 6)
  - Mead Johnson--BuSpar--Post-It pad, undated (Box 6)
  - Merck Sharp & Dohme--Indocin--Desk object with hand, undated (Box 6)
  - Mount Sinai Medical Center--Annenburg Building Steel-Topping commemorative nut and bolt, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Pharmacia--Letter opener, undated (Box 6)
  - Schering--Meticorten/Meticortelene/Sigmagen--12"/300mm ruler, undated (Box 6)
  - Stuart Pharmaceuticals--Effersyllium--12"/300mm ruler, undated (Box 6)
  - Unidentified--Plastic colon model, undated (Box 6)
  - American Cyanamide--Maxzide--Coffee mug, undated (Box 7)
  - C.B. Fleet--Phospho-Soda--Measuring cup, undated (Box 7)
  - Eli Lilly--Trinsicon--Paperweight, undated (Box 7)
  - G.D. Searle--Lomotil--Message in a Bottle, undated (Box 7)
  - Mead Johnson--Desyrel--Paperclip holder, undated (Box 7)
  - K-Lyte DS--Bausch & Lomb magnifying glass for reading, undated (Box 7)
  - Merck Sharp & Dohme--Trinalin--Coffee mug, undated (Box 7)
  - National Instrument Company--Thermometer, undated (Box 7)
  - Pet Milk Compaly--Pet Milk--Child's cup, undated (Box 7)
  - Schering--Chlor-Trimeton--Metric converter pencil cup, undated (Box 7)
  - Squibb--Capoten--Coffee mug, undated (Box 7)
  - Wellcome--Sudafed--glass, undated (Box 7)
- Oversize Materials, 1942-1986 and undated; 3; 3 boxes
  - Abbott Laboratories--Football players print, 1942 (Box 8)
  - Arlington Chemical--Liquid Peptonoids--Promotion featuring translation of tract from Hippocrates, undated (Box 8)
  - Chicago Sun Times--Reprint of Alan Shepard space flight cover, 1961 May 6 (Box 8)
  - Ciba-Geigy--Calendars, 1961-1982 (Box 8)
  - G.D. Searle--Flagyl/Lomotil--Reproduction of 15th century drawing of pregnant woman, undated (Box 8)
  - G.D. Searle--Floraquin--Etiology of Leukorrhea diagnostic chart, undated (Box 8)
  - Hoechst Pharmaceuticals --Calendars, 1972-1982; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Hoechst Pharmaceuticals --Doxidan--Parchment reproduction of George Washington's call to arms, undated (Box 8)
  - Lloyd Brothers--Doxidan--In the Days of Tutenkhamon pamphlet series (illustrated by Nina M. Davis), 1965 (Box 8)
  - Reed & Carnrick--The Digestive System wall chart, undated (Box 8)
  - Roche Laboratories--Valium--Classic and Current Concepts featuring prints of Vesalius woodcuts, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Smith Kline & French--Calendars, 1976, 1979 (Box 8)
  - American Medical Association--Poster, Keep Politics Out of This Picture [opposition to compulsory health insurance], undated (Box 9)
  - Columbia University Medical School--A Schematic Presentation of Some Forms of Allergic Reaction, undated (Box 9)
  - G.D. Searle--Lomotil--Anti-Diarrhea poster and pamphlet, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Glaxo--Poster, Digestive Disease Week, A Night in Old New Orleans (feature print of Andre Derain, Landscape at Cassis, 1907), 1984 (Box 10)
  - Ortho Pharmaceutical--Print, The Gathering Storm: Long Island (Bruce Crane), undated (Box 10)
  - Roche Laboratories--Limbitrol--Depression poster, 1986 (Box 10)